Guide to the Everett Education Association Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Everett Education Association records
1937-1992
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
3849
Everett Education Association (Everett, Wash.)
30.06 cubic feet
Records of the Everett Education Association
Organized into 6 accessions.
Accession No. 3849-001, Everett Education Association records, 1937-1947
Accession No. 3849-002, United Teachers of Everett records, circa 1971-1986
Accession No. 3849-003, Everett Education Association records, circa 1970-1972
Accession No. 3849-004, United Teachers of Everett records, 1986-1990
Accession No. 3849-005, Everett Education Association/United Teachers of Everett records, 1978-1992
Accession No. 3849-006, United Teachers of Everett records, 1975-1992
Bargaining files, budget files, cartoon, clippings, conferences and conventions, correspondence, dues files, historical features, logo design, membership files, memoranda of understanding, memos, minutes, newsletters, program materials, reports, resolutions, subject files, subject series, surveys.
No restrictions on access.
Everett Education Association (Everett, Wash.)$vArchives; Everett Education Association (Everett, Wash.)$xMembership; Everett Education Association (Everett, Wash.)$xFinance; Teachers' unions$zWashington (State)$zSnohomish County; Teachers$zWashington (State)$zSnohomish County; Education$zWashington (State)$zSnohomish County; Labor$zWashington (State)$zSnohomish County; Labor unions$zWashington (State)$zSnohomish County; Labor movement$zWashington (State)$zSnohomish County; Records (Documents); Minutes (Records); Business correspondence; Collective labor agreements; Ephemera; Newsletters; Annual reports; Merrick, Bryant; Morrill, John; Sells, Mike; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); AFL-CIO.$bWashington State Labor Council; American Federation of Teachers.$bLocal 772 (Everett, Wash.); Everett Education Association (Everett, Wash.)$vArchives; Everett Grade Teachers Club; Everett High School Teachers' Association; Everett Public Schools; National Education Association; Pilchuk Uniserv Council; Snohomish County Central Labor Council; United Teachers of Everett; Washington Education Association; Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Primary and Secondary Education; Civic Activism; Washington (State)
- Everett Education Association records, 1937-1947; 3849-001; .14 cubic foot
  Minutes of Everett Grade Teachers Club 1937-1947, and Everett High School Teachers' Association 1938-1943. These organizations were precursors to Everett Education Association.
  Open to all users.
  Donated by the Association, 11/10/1986.
  - MINUTES, 1983-1992; SERIES I (Box-folder 1/1-1/3)
    - Minutes - Everett Grade Teachers Club, 1937-1942 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Minutes - Everett Grade Teachers Club, 1943-1947 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Minutes - Everett High School Teachers Assocation, 1938-1943 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - MEMBERSHIP MATERIALS, 1941; SERIES II (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Resignation from President Position Letter from J.S. Blue, 1941 (Box-folder 1/4)
- United Teachers of Everett records, circa 1971-1986; 1973-1986; 3849-002; 22.00 cubic feet
  Correspondence, minutes, bargaining files, subject files, newsletters, clippings, subject series.
  Donated by the Association, 10/27/1988.
  - National Education Association - Washington Education Association - Everett Education Association Memorandum of Agreement, 1979; Founding documentation with budget and objectives, outlining chain of command; Copied personal letter regarding memorandum (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Founding Documentation - United Teachers of Everett Labor Caucus, Outline of how the Everett Education Association will support the United Teachers of Everett Labor Caucus (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence, 1973-1974; Mostly photo-copies of letters sent, although some originals are included. Primarily letters to the Superintendent and Everett school board regarding improper or unfair hiring practices and letters to the WEA and NEA regarding delegations and invitations (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Contract Correspondence – Incoming, 1975; Mostly original documents, includes the 1974-1975 Everett certified staff salary scales, discussion of the grievance process and correspondence with the Everett Federation of Teachers (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence, 1976-1977; Photo and carbon copies of records regarding contract negotiations on holidays, school schedules, and the leave policy; thank you letters to other education associations and to guest speakers at a retirement seminar that was held. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence, 1974-1975; Carbon copies and some photo copies of information on affirmative action, financial information, EFT, class sizes, substitute teachers and staff evaluations,Everett Education Association revised by-laws (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence, 1975-1976; Photo and carbon copies regarding individual contracts, teacher surveys, membership enrollment, and business transactions, newspaper from WEA (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Everett Education Association Received Correspondence, 1975-1976; Photocopies, and some originals of documents regarding levy agreements, contract bartering, strikes, EFT, and appointments (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Everett Education Association Received Correspondence, 1977-1978; Letters, legal documents (restraining order) and memos, originals and copies, regarding tuition vouture legislation and Everett teachers strike (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Everett Education Association Received Correspondence, 1978-1979; letters, job postings, memorandums regarding Iran, schedules and events, and organization elections (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Everett Education Association Received Correspondence, 1976-1977; Letters regarding the Everett teachers strike, funding for the strike, talks with the EFT, and several directories (Everett Education Association, WEA) and agendas (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - NEA Now Newsletter, 1978; Collection of bi-weekly newsletters focusing on national education issues, but highlighting local education organizations and issues (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence, 1977-1978; Primarily copies of letters sent by the Everett Education Association regarding contracts, strike / contract negotiation support, and drivers education / class schedule contracts (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence, 1978-1979; copies and original letters regarding membership, budgets, and letters of thanks, strike information, court case regarding strike costs (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Everett Education Association Received Correspondence - Part 1, 1978-1979; regional newsletters, organizational structures, court photos, nea v. Marshall memo, strike stoppage contract, strike costs,letters of support for the strike, letters against the strike (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Everett Education Association Received Correspondence - Part 2, 1978-1978; strike stoppage contract, strike costs, packet of strike support letters, letters against the strike, levy information, EFT letters (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Everett School District Job Postings, 1978-1979; copies of job postings including qualifications, duties, and responsibilities for a variety of positions (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Received Information - Part 1, 1982; copy of a speech, blank survey forms, sign up sheets, WA Senate proposed education budget, budget and tax commentary, copies of legislative bills (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Received Information - Part 2, 1982; Snohomish County Employment and Training Admin. meeting minutes, various organizations newsletters, levy information and mandatory schooling (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sent Correspondence of Mike Sells, 1982; Collection of letters regarding teacher hiring, Everett Education Association meetings agendas, grievances, and order requests (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pilchuck Uniserve Documents, 1982; vouchers, meeting agendas and minutes, letters and funding (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Superintendent of Public Instruction - Education costs, 1982; Tables of costs per school district and per country with explanations and percents and county treasury reports (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Everett Education Association Received Information, 1980-1981; Letters regarding collective bargaining and layoffs, extended leave information, substitutes, and a candidate endorsement list (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence, 1979-1981; Press releases, letters pertaining to layoffs, re-hiring of laid-off workers, payroll, and leave time (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence, 1979-1980; Letters regarding Everett Education Association / EFT combining documentation, women’s leadership, expense lists, membership recruitment, collective bargaining info (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Everett Education Association Received Correspondence, 1979-1980; Letters regarding contracts, election endorsements, grievances, address changes, some discoloration stains on letters (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - United Way of Snohomish County Information, 1981; Requests for money, budgets, and meeting minutes (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Pilchuck Uniserve Council Sent Correspondence, 1981-1982; Role of classified employees in WEA, bargaining, employment levels and types, grievances (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence - Part 1, 1981-1982; Copies of letters regarding health insurance, legislative discussions, laws and budgets, staff transfers, Everett School District Goals and objectives list (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence - Part 2, 1981-1982; Copies of letters regarding retirement, grievance hearings, Everett Education Association representative election process (by school), joint PTA – Everett Education Association meeting, contract edits, sick leave, and unemployment benefits and questionnai (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Everett Education Association Received Correspondence, 1981; Letters and documents, most original, regarding alcohol licenses, salary scale, employment and training administration information, surveys from league of Women voters re: education, special education, faculty assignments, and correspondence with legislat (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Salary and Levy Lids, 1981; Documents, laws, and actions by the Superintendent of Public Instruction regarding the state salary cap and the Everett School District levy (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Received Information - Part 1, 1982; Requests for funding from the United Way of Snohomish County, PATCO support, Henry Jackson 1982 re-election campaign information, human resource information and policies, response letters from members of congress, (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Received Information - Part 2, 1982; Budgets, conference registration forms, meeting minutes and agendas for a variety of organizations, founding documents of M-2 Job Therapy of Snohomish County, (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Received Information - Part 3, 1982; Meeting agendas and minutes, labor film material / TV requests, Everett Housing Authority documents, new union charters (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence - Part 1, 1982; Mostly copies of letters inviting / reminding people of events, letters asking groups to drop reduction in force lawsuits, and letters to retiring teachers (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondence - Part 2, 1982; Mostly copies of letters, some originals, regarding representatives (building and conference), dropping lawsuits, and contract negotiations (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Received Correspondence, 1982-1983; Court cases and legal documents regarding teacher hiring, 38th leg. District Democratic committee by laws, National labor union conference information (NEA, AFL-CIO), Bellevue bargaining survey to teachers, United Way funding requests (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sent Correspondence - Part 1, 1982-1983; Letters from the Everett Education Association regarding in-school writing programs, collective bargaining, diversity programs, meeting minutes, and agendas (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sent Correspondence - Part 2, 1981-1983; Collective bargaining, religious leave, coach's salaries, reduction in force, benefits packages, substitutes, role in the 1982 election (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pilchuk Uniserv Council Internal Correspondence, 1982-1983; Letter to the editor, collective bargaining / negotiation training and tools, sick leave, meeting minutes, House Bill 21 legislative responses and opinions, role of educators in elections (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Everett Education Association Received Correspondence, 1983; Letters regarding early childhood education, meeting times and minutes, article on education as a political issue, sexual abuse treatment, employee census, education legislation summary, contract parts (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Everett Education Association Leave Requests, 1982-1983; Copies of leave requests to the Everett School District for employees for Everett Education Association related events (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondences, 1983; Welcome letters to new staff, pre-school year and start of school year contract negotiations information, and insurance information (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Received Information, 1983-1984; Events calendar, Luther Child Center Sexual Abuse information, meeting minutes and agendas, letters regarding the legislative session, anti drinking and drugs campaign, United Way information, and Union Teacher Press Association roster (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pilchuk Uniserv Council Internal Information, 1983-1984; Pilchuck Uniserv meeting reminders and minutes, recruitment, bargaining, information on grievances, and budget information (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Letters - Part 1, 1983-1984; Leave time, child labor and careers, Everett Education Association elections and positions, insurance information, coaches pay, teachers salary scale, and school levy information (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Letters - Part 2, 1983-1984; News article on public perception of education, article on merit pay in education, bargaining process, responses to comments about the bargaining process, and school board candidate interview information (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Collected Documents - Part 1, 1983; United Way funding requests, Washington State handicapped student report, labor book catalogue, NEA and biased curriculum, unbalanced taxes, and a report on sexually abused children (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Collected Documents - Part 2, 1983; United Way meeting minutes and survey, organizational assessment, letters from Everett School District re: bargaining, court case information, labor / media handbook, WEA legislative handbook (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondences, 1983; Letters regarding collective bargaining, sick days, membership information, collective bargaining court case, tax allocations, grievances, coaches, and student writing (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Received Information, 1984; Uniserv representative application, political campaign information, Eastern Washington University survey on strikes, promotion process information, report on salaries and benefits, Everett subsidized housing information, and the role of labor in the era o (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Pilchuck Uniserv Council Information, 1984; Meeting minutes, budgets, bargaining strategies, Monroe “Table Talk” newsletters, and benefits comparison report (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Everett Education Association, 1984; Letters regarding meeting times, campaign endorsements, staffing information, insurance, and conference information (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Everett Education Association Received letters and Information, 1985; Election thank you letters, medical benefits, and grant reference forms (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Pilchuck UniServ Internal Information, 1986; Memos regarding meeting agendas, salary increases, budget reports, classified employees, probation, and structural changes through WEA and the National Labor Relations Board (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondences, 1986; Memos and letters regarding leave requests, conduct cases, National Education Association conference information and collective bargaining, survey of benefits, letters to the editor, and article on collective bargaining in higher education (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Everett Education Association Received Information, 1985-1986; Seatbelt law info, precinct voting chairs, various newsletters, annual state salary scale, Gramm-Rudman amendment, Christa McAuliffe lesson agenda from space, national elementary school recognition program and survey (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Correspondences, 1986; Completed NEA grant application, memos regarding special programs concerns over collective bargaining, teacher mentor program, scheduling and Everett Education Association meetings, letter to the editor, weather make-up days, salary schedules, student mil (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Everett Education Association Organizational Documents, 1977-1978; Lists of Everett Education Association building representatives, bargaining team, and officers, meeting minutes and agendas for Everett Education Association Executive Board and Representative Council meetings, Everett Education Association budget reports (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Everett Education Association Organizational Documents, 1976-1977; Meeting minutes and agendas for Everett Education Association Executive Board and Representative Council, Everett Education Association budget reports and newsletters, teacher evaluation form for the Everett School District, letters regarding collective b (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Everett Education Association Organizational Documents, 1974-1976; Budget reports, Executive board and representative council meeting agendas and minutes (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Received Information - Part 1, 1985; Memos regarding international conflicts, math and science funding, Everett Chamber of Commerce, adult and special education funding, retirement funds, Expo ’86, and the 1985-1987 Washington State budget proposal (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Received Information - Part 2, 1985; Memos from Superintendent of Public Instruction regarding teacher exchanges, migrant students, school certification, and interruptions in instructional time, letters of concern with idea of annual teacher contract (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Received Information - Part 3, 1985; Washington Education Association Presidential election information, Pilchuck UniServ funding allocations, computer software for schools (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Pilchuck UniServ Memos, 1985; Memos regarding meeting minutes, budgets, contract negotiation structure changes, and collective bargaining (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Memos Part 1, 1985; Copies of memos from Mike Sells, President Everett Education Association, regarding recruitment, retirement funds, insurance concerns, and retirement social invitations (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Memos Part 2, 1985; Copies of memos regarding Everett Education Association elections, insurance and benefits programs, other labor organizations, retirement funding, leave requests, and class size committee reports (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Everett Education Association Received Information, 1985; Letters regarding teacher evaluations, information from other labor organizations, school accreditation applications, House Joint Resolution 22 - changes in levy voting laws, school board elections, cost of living report (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Pilchuck UniServe Memos, 1985; Pilchuck UniServ budget report, legislative concerns, meeting announcements, information on House Joint Resolution 22, unified bargaining guidelines, list of education acronyms, grievances guide and issue (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Memos Part 1, 1985-1986; Copies of sent memos regarding kindergarten teachers, Everett Education Association representatives, class sizes, other labor organizations, candidate endorsements, list of new members (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Everett Education Association Sent Memos Part 2, 1985-1986; Copies of sent memos regarding starting teacher salaries, new Everett Education Association members, future of Everett Education Association Labor Caucus, school board candidate interview questions, congressional concerns and contacts (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Everett Education Association Organizational Documents Part 1, 1975-1976; Budget reports, Executive board and representative council meeting agendas and minutes, newsletters, and bi-laws (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Everett Education Association Organizational Documents Part 2, 1975-1976; Budget reports, Executive board and representative council meeting agendas and minutes, newsletters, and bi-laws (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Everett Education Association Critical Documents, 1978-1979; List of board members, building representatives, members, press releases, Everett Education Association election materials, descriptions of Everett Education Association responsibilities, salary scale, collective bargaining recommendations, political acti (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Everett Education Association Leadership Information, Undated; Confrontation description, ballot, Everett Education Association contact list, interview information, public opinion phone survey outline (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Everett Education Association Executive Board Records, 1976-1979; Executive board agendas, minutes, goals and objectives, and memos regarding meeting times (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Everett Education Association Representative Council Records, 1978-1979; Representative council agendas, minutes, memos regarding meetings (time and place) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Everett Education Association Budget Reports, 1978-1979; Monthly and annual budget reports and school calendar (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Everett Education Association All School Publications, 1978-1979; Various newsletters, Everett Education Association election information, event announcements, and levy information (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Everett Education Association Grievance Committee, 1978-1979; Documents regarding how to write a grievance complaint, committee guidelines, handbook for grievance representatives, meeting reminders, and case studies (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Everett Education Association Membership Information, 1978-1979; Everett Education Association membership lists, dues information, and a list of membership categories (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Everett Education Association Representative Council Records, 1979-1980; List of representatives and goals, copies of agendas, record of meeting minutes, and Everett Education Association election information (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Everett Education Association Executive Board Records, 1979-1980; List of board members, meeting calendar, agendas and meeting minutes, school board election information, statement of educational philosophy rough draft (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Everett Education Association Budget Reports, 1979-1980; Budget reports and preliminary budgets (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Everett All-School Publications, 1979-1980; Collection of newsletters and letters posted for all teachers, Shortwaves weekly newsletter, salary scale, Uniserve News, information on school board elections, political action committee, Staff Report, and school board briefings (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Everett Education Association Bi-Laws, 1978-1980; Documents regarding bi-law revision process and changes (Box 4, Folder 12)